Alliance Against Women's Oppression Records, 1980-1989
Sophia Smith Collection
Alliance Against Women's Oppression records
1980-1989
Alliance Against Women's Oppression
MS 699
5.75 linear ft.
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
International women of color organization, Welfare rights activists, Reproductive rights and Women's health advocates. The Records are primarily related to the Bay Area Chapter of the Alliance and contain documents that articulate and demonstrate the challenges of developing a revolutionary mass organization through position and discussion papers, drafts, and publications produced by the Alliance. There is abundant documentation of the processes of coalition and social investigation that AAWO engaged in reproductive rights advocacy. The collection is rich in documentation of the organization Somos Hermanas in Nicaragua. Types of materials include committee reports; meeting notes; political discussion papers; study guides.
In August of 1980, the Alliance Against Women's Oppression (AAWO) was formed out of a process of transformation and struggle begun in the Third World Women's Alliance (TWWA) in late 1979. The newly formed organization resolved to focus its organizing activities primarily on the struggle for women's rights and equality and against the racialized, gendered, classed sexism of the developed North. The AAWO announced itself as a multi-racial alliance of lesbian and straight women. Women of color lesbian issues that had been stubbornly ignored by the mainstream women's movement were part of the political line of the AAWO.
Continuing work initiated and produced by the TWWA, the AAWO persistently clarified the intersectionality of race, gender, class, and sexuality in its political analysis of capitalism and the conditions of women in the transnational economy. AAWO work areas included infant mortality, reproductive rights, sterilization abuse, Central American and African Women's liberation struggles, and Lesbian and Gay rights. The AAWO also continued the political education work of International Women's Day (IWD). AAWO members produced discussion and position papers for AAWO members and the public. AAWO had chapters in Boston, New York, Louisville, Seattle, and Washington, D.C.
In order to take up the struggle of women's oppression nationally and internationally, AAWO created coalitions and joined their efforts with other social justice organizations locally and globally. Some of the organizations they were closely associated with were Somos Hermanas, the Nicaraguan Women's Association (AMNLAE), MADRE, South African Women's Organization, Line of March (LOM), and the National Campaign to Restore Abortion Funding (NCRAF). The AAWO identified itself with socialist, womanist/feminist politics, and provisionally based their political line on a Marxist class analysis.
The AAWO joined their efforts with the Reproductive Rights National Network (R2N2) to advocate for abortion rights for low-income women while also calling attention to the involuntary sterilization of migrant and immigrant women of color. In 1984 in response to the U.S.'s continuing intervention in Nicaragua, AAWO organized a delegation, Somos Hermanas, in alliance with the Nicaraguan women's mass organization, AMNLAE.
AAWO dissolved by 1990. The Women of Color Resource Center (1989 to present) was formed with some members from the TWWA and AAWO. Activist organizational work stretching back to the civil rights movement, the Black Women's Caucus of SNCC, the Third World Women's Alliance and the Alliance Against Women's Oppression was evident in the activist and advocacy politics of the Women of Color Resource Center.
The Alliance against Women's Oppression Records consists of 5.75 linear ft. and are primarily related to the Bay Area Chapter of the Alliance. The collection contains many documents that articulate and demonstrate the challenges of developing a revolutionary mass organization. The collection is a good source of position and discussion papers, drafts, and AAWO publications, produced by the Alliance. The "United Front Against War and Racism" is a political discussion paper that articulates some of AAWO's political strategy. Through the Coalition Against Infant Mortality (CFIM), 1979 - 1982, AAWO continued the infant mortality activism begun in the TWWA. For the beginnings of this important project of the AAWO, see the TWWA Records also held by the Sophia Smith Collection.
The collection has abundant documentation of the processes of coalition and social investigation that AAWO engaged in reproductive rights advocacy. The collection is rich in documentation of Somos Hermanas's activities in Nicaragua. Types of materials include committee reports; meeting notes; political discussion papers; study guides.
The bulk of the papers date from 1983 to 1988 and focus on the Alliance's many projects organizing activities primarily on the struggle for third world women's rights and equality nationally and internationally.
This collection is organized into seven series:
I. ADMINISTRATIVE MATERIALS
II. POLITICAL PAPERS
III. PUBLICATIONS
IV. AFFILIATED ORGANIZATIONS
V. SUBJECTS
VI. PHOTOGRAPHS
VII. OVERSIZE
The Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Cheryl Johnson, Vicki Alexander, Barbara Morita, and Melanie Tervalon donated records to the Women of Color Resource Center Collection/Archives which were then donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by the Third World Women's Alliance Alumni Association Archives Committee.
Abortion -- United States; African American women -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources; Asian American women -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources; Birth control -- United States -- History -- Sources; Civil rights -- United States -- History -- Sources; Ethnicity -- United States; Infants -- Mortality -- History; Hispanic American women -- History -- United States -- Sources; Indian women -- United States -- Social conditions -- History; International economic relations; International Women's Day -- History; Latin American women -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources; Minority women -- United States -- History -- Sources; Reproductive health -- History -- Sources; Sterilization (birth control) -- History -- Sources; United States -- Race relations; Welfare rights movement -- United States -- History -- Sources; Women -- Economic conditions -- 20th century; Women -- El Salvador -- Social conditions; Women -- International cooperation; Women -- Health and hygiene -- Developing countries; Women -- Health and hygiene -- United States; Women -- Political activity -- United States -- History -- Sources; Women's health services -- United States -- History -- Sources; Women's rights -- Developing countries; Working class women -- United States -- History -- Sources; Alliance Against the Oppression of Women (U.S.); Third World Women's Alliance; Jones, Diane; Morita, Barbara; Tervalon, Melanie
Additional records are housed at the Mary McLeod Bethune Council House - National Archives for Black Women's History, Amistad Research Center, and Duke University. Related materials in the SSC include Voices of Feminism interviews with Frances Beal and Linda Burnham, and the Third World Women's Alliance Records.
- SERIES I. ADMISTRATIVE MATERIALS 1979-1988, 4.25 linear feet
  This series consists of the organization's reports, financial materials, meeting agendas, meeting notes, histories, and committee reports. The bulk of sub series Committees is comprised of organizational materials from the Coalition to Fight Infant Mortality (CFIM). The CFIM was originally organized within the Third World Women's Alliance (TWWA) and continued its work when the TWWA disbanded and reformed as the AAWO. Among the CFIM files are their community investigation into Alameda County's high mortality rate, correspondence to and from the Alameda County Grand Jury, the Grand Jury report, the Alameda County Health Care Services Agency report to the board of supervisors of the Alameda County Hospital, and the house hearings on infant mortality. The subseries, Reproductive Rights contains information from national committees that fought for reproductive rights such as the Action Committee for Abortion Rights (ACAR), the National Committee to Restore Abortion Funding (NCRAF), the Reproductive Rights National Network (R2N2) and the Seattle Reproductive Rights Alliance (SRRA). The subseries Somos Hermanas contains memos, correspondence, publications and planning notes from the organization, as well as photos and details from a delegation's trip to Nicaragua in 1986.
- SERIES II. POLITICAL PAPERS 1982-undated, .25 linear feet
  This series consists of papers created by the AAWO on issues that they recognized as intersecting with their goals.
- SERIES III. PUBLICATIONS 1963-88, .25 linear feet
  This series consists of brochures, discussion papers, flyers, the history of the organization and other publications produced by the group.
- SERIES IV. AFFILIATED ORGANIZATIONS 1980-1987, .5 linear feet
  This series consists of information on, and publications from, the organizations listed in the finding aid.
- SERIES V. SUBJECTS 1978-1985, undated, .25 linear feet
  This series consists of research materials on the subjects listed.
- VI. PHOTOGRAPHS 1984-1986, undated, .25 linear feet
  This series consists of undated group photographs.
- VII. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  Consists of posters from Nicaragua.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION
  - Committees
    - Coalition to fight infant mortality (CFIM) 1978-1984, undated, [hand written notes in CFIM attributed to Barbara Morita and Melanie Tervalon]
      - AAWO assessments, 1979 - 82, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - ACHCSA report to board of supervisors, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Children's hospital, 1981 - 82, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Community investigation, I-Team, 1979-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
      - First National Conference on Black Women's Health Issues 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Grand jury correspondence and report, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - House hearings on infant mortality, 26 Mar 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Letters and statements of support, 1978-80 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Newsletter, clippings, press releases, 1979-84, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - International women's day committee (WCCIWD)
      - International women's day (IWD), 1981-88, undated (Box 2, Folder 3-8)
    - Kwanza committee, 1979-81, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Lesbian/gay task force, 1981-86, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Nairobi, third world conference on women, 1985
      - Notes, articles, and memos (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Conference Materials (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Reproductive rights, 1982-86, undated
      - Action committee for abortion rights (ACAR), 1981-85 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
      - National campaign to restore abortion funding, (NCRAF), 1984-87, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - National campaign to restore abortion funding (NCRAF), 1984-87, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Reproductive rights national network (R2N2), 1982-84, undated (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
      - Rosie Jimenez-October 3rd coalition, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Seattle reproductive rights alliance (SRRA), 1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Steering Committee, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Somos Hermanas, 1984-88
      - AAWO memos 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Development plans and memoranda 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Louisville chapter, 1986-1987, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Nicaragua delegation, health colloquium, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Nicaragua delegation, member notes, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Nicaragua delegation, photographs 1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Nicaragua delegation, orientation 1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Organization notes, national 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
      - Publications 1985-1989, undated (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - World peace congress, Copenhagen 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Financial material, 1983-1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Histories, 1980; 1989; undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Meetings, 1981-88
    - Chapter meetings
      - Bay area 1981-88 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Summation meeting, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
      - Boston, MA, 1988, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Louisville, KY, 1988-89, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - New York, NY, 1988, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Washington, D.C., 1985-86, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - National meetings
      - First national congress, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Second national congress, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Second national congress, continued 1986 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - National council, 1983-84 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - National council, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - National council, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - National council, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - National council, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
      - Executive, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Executive, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Executive, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Executive, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Executive, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Member's notebook, Diane Jones, Bay area, 1983-88 (Box 8, Folder 4-9)
  - Membership, 1981, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Chants and songs, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Stationary, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Propaganda and educational work, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - South African women's day, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Study guides
    - Study guides 1981, 1982, undated (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
    - Member's notebook, Diane Jones, Bay area, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Orientation seminar, undated (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - Substance abuse task force, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Zionism, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- SERIES II. POLITICAL PAPERS
  - Israeli invasion of Lebanon, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Reproductive rights, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - United front against war and racism, (UFAWR) undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Women's liberation and the worldwide struggle against imperialism, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
- SERIES III. PUBLICATIONS
  - Brochures, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Discussion papers, 1983-87 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Flyers, 1987, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Our History, undated [also located in history folder] (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Women's voices from Nairobi, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 20)
- SERIES IV. AFFILIATED ORGANIZATIONS
  - Associación de mujeres de El Salvador (AMES), 1983, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Associación de mujeres Nicaraguenses (AMNLAE), 1980-88, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Jesse Jackson presidential campaign(JJC), 1984-88, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Rainbow coalition (JJC), 1985-87 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Line of March (LOM), 1984; 1989; undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Publications, LOM, Frontline, 1983-87 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Women's commission, LOM, 1988-89, undated (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - Madre, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Women's Building of the Bay Area, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- SERIES V. SUBJECTS
  - Feminization of poverty, 1978, 1983, 1984, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Gay/Lesbian, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Middle East/Palestine, 1985, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Reproductive rights, 1985, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Socialist feminism, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - South African women, 1984, 1985, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Soviet women, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Zimbabwe women, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
- SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - MEP, 1984; IWD, 1986 [some photos in Somos Hermanas; Louisville chapter] (Box 12)
- SERIES VII. OVERSIZE
  - Posters
    - Women to Women: Guatemalan Women Speak1983 (Map-case Flate file)
    - Guerilla Madre (Map-case Flate file)
    - CPF #2 (Map-case Flate file)